If you run the learning algorithm
and it doesn't do as well
as you are hoping, almost all
the time it will be because
you have either a high bias
problem or a high variance problem.
In other words they're either an
underfitting problem or an overfitting problem.
And in this case it's very
important to figure out
which of these two problems is
bias or variance or a bit of both that you
actually have.
Because knowing which of these
two things is happening would give
a very strong indicator for whether
the useful and promising ways
to try to improve your algorithm.
In this video, I would like
to delve more deeply into
this bias and various issue and
understand them better as well
as figure out how to look
at and evaluate knows whether or not we might have a bias problem or a variance problem.
Since this would be critical to
figuring out how to improve the performance of learning algorithm that you implement.
So you've already
seen this figure a few times,
where if you fit two simple
hypothesis, like a straight line that that underfits the data.
If you fit a two complex
hypothesis, then that might
fit the training set perfectly but
overfit the data and this
may be hypothesis of some
intermediate level of complexity,
of some, maybe degree two
polynomials are not too low and not too high degree.
That's just right.
And gives you the best
generalization error out of these options.
Now that we're armed with the
notion of training and validation
in test sets, we can understand
the concepts of bias and variance a little bit better.
Concretely, let our
training error and cross
validation error be defined as
in the previous videos, just say,
the squared error, the average
squared error as measured
on the 20 sets or as
measured on the cross validation set.
Now let's plot the following figure.
On the horizontal axis I am
going to plot the degree of polynomial,
so as I go the right
I'm going to be fitting higher and higher order polynomials.
So will the left of this figure, where maybe D equals one, we're
going to be fitting very simple figures.Whereas way here on the right of the
horizontal axis, have much larger values of D. So a much higher degree of
polynomial. And so here that's going to correspond to fitting. Much more complex
functions to your training set. Let's look at the training error and the cross
validation error and plot them on this figure. Let's start with the training
error. As we increase the degree of the polynomial, we're going to be able to fit
our training set better and better. And so, if D=1 then it's a relatively high
training error. If we have a very high degree polynomial our training error is
going to be really low maybe even zero because we'll fit the training set really well.
And so as we increase the degree of polynomial, we find typically that the
training error decreases. So, I'm going to write J. Subscript three of data there.
Because our training error tends to decrease with the degree of polynomial
that we fit to the data. Next let's look at the cross validation error. Or for that
matter, if we look at the test set error we'll get a pretty similar result as if we
were to plot the cross validation error. So, we know that if D=1. We're fitting a
very simple function. And so we may be under fitting the training set. And so
we're going to have a very high cross validation error. If we fit, you know, an
intermediate degree polynomial, there's, we have a D equals two in our example on
the previous slide, we're going to have a much lower cross validation error, because
we're just fitting, finding a much better fit to the data. And conversely, if D were
too high, so if D took on, say, a value of four, then we're getting over fitting, and
so we ended with a high value for cross validation error. So, if you were to. vary
this smoothly and plot the curve. You might end up with a curve like that. Where,
that's J.C.V. Of staza. Indicating that you plot J. Tesla's data, you get
something very similar. And so, this sort of plot also helps us to better understand
the notions of bias and variance. Concretely, suppose you've applied a
learning algorithm, and it's not performing as well as you were hoping.
So, if your cross-validation set error, or your test set error is high. How can we
figure out if the learning algorithm is suffering from high bias or if it's suffer
from high variance? So the setting of the cause validation error being high,
corresponds to either this regime or this regime. So this regime on the left
corresponds to a high bias problem. That is, if you're fitting a overly low order
polynomial, such as a D=1. When we really needed a higher order polynomial to fit
the data. Whereas in contrast, this regime corresponds to a high variance problem.
That is, if D, the degree of polynomial was too large for the data set that we
have. And this figure just has a clue for how to distinguish between these two
cases. Concretely for the high bias case.That is the case of under fitting. What we
find is that both the cross validation error and the trading error are going to
be high. So if your algorithm is suffering from a bias problem. The training set
error, will be high. And you might find that the cross validation error will also
be high. It might be a close. Maybe just slightly higher than a training error. And
so, if you see this combination that's a sign your algorithm may be suffering from
high bias. In contrast if your algorithm is suffering from high variance then if
you look here. We'll notice that J-train that is the training error is going to be
low. That is your fitting the training set very well. Where as your, cross validation
error. Assuming that this is say the squared era. Which we're trying to
minimize . Where as in contrast, your error on the cross
validation set or your cross function in the cross validation set will be much bigger
Than your training set error. So, there's a double greater than sign. That's the
math symbol for much greater than, denoted by two greater than signs. And so, if you
see this combination of values then that might give you, that's a clue that your
learning algorithm maybe suffering from high variance. And might be over
emphasizing. And the key that distinguishes these two cases is if you
have a high bias problem your training set error will also be high. Your hypothesis
is just not fitting the training set well. And if you have a high variance problem.
Your training set error will usually be low. That is much lower than your cross
validation error. So hopefully that gives you a somewhat better understanding of the
two problems of bias and variants. I still have a lot more to say about bias and
variants in the next few videos. But what we'll see later is that by diagnosing
whether a learning algorithm may be suffering from high bias or high variance,
we'll show you even more details of how to do that in later videos. We'll see that by
figuring out whether a learning algorithm may be suffering from high bias or high
variance, or a combination of both, that, that would give us much better guidance
promising things to try in order to improve the performance of a learning algorithm.